<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/master/src/out/critical.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/master/src/out/critical.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>III, P. 2, Inq. 3, T. 2, S. 2, Q. 1, T. 3, D. 2, M. 3, C. 1</title>
        <author ref="#AlexanderOfHales">Alexander of Hales</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name xml:id="JW">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>TEI encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>III, P. 2, Inq. 3, T. 2, S. 2, Q. 1, T. 3, D. 2, M. 3, C. 1</title>
          <date when="2017-10-16">October 16, 2017</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>
          <ref target="https://www.earlyfranciscans.com">ERC Project 714427: Authority and Innovation in Early Franciscan Thought</ref>
        </authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International</ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="Qd" n="quaracchi1948d">Quaracchi 1948, Volume 4</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-critical-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/master/src/out/critical.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
        guidelines for a critical edition.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2017-10-16" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on"/>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1">
        <head xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-Hd1e102">III, P. 2, Inq. 3, T. 2, S. 2, Q. 1, T. 3, D. 2, M. 3, C. 1</head>
        <head xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-Hd1e105" type="question-title">WHETHER IT IS LAWFUL TO WAGE WAR.</head>
        <p xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-d1e108">
          Therefore, it is asked whether it is lawful to wage war.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-d1e113">
          To this, a. <name ref="#Augustine">Augustine</name>, <title>Ad Bonifacium</title>:
          <quote xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-Qd1e120">Do not think that no one can please God,
            who serves with the weapons of war.
            Among them was holy David,
            to whom the Lord gave such great testimony;
            among them were also many righteous men of that time</quote>,
          such as Joshua, to whom it is said in <title>Exod.</title> 17, 9:
          <quote>Go out and fight against Amalek and the others</quote>;
          likewise,
          <quote xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-Qd1e133">among them was that Centurion,
            who said to the Lord:
            <quote>I am not worthy that you should enter under my roof</quote></quote>,
          <title>Matth.</title> 8, 8.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-d1e141">
          b. Likewise, <name ref="#Augustine">Augustine</name>, <title>Ad eumdem Bonifacium</title>:
          <quote xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-Qd1e150">John does not order soldiers to give up their arms,
            and Christ, after the tribute money, <title>Matth.</title> 22, 21,
            advises that it be rendered to Caesar,
            because pay is provided to the soldier on account of necessary wars</quote>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-d1e161">
          c. Likewise,
          <quote xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-Qd1e165"><name ref="#Augustine">Augustine</name>, in the sermon <title>De puero Centurionis</title>:
            If Christian discipline condemned all wars,
            this would rather be the advice given in the Gospel for salvation to those asking,
            <title>Luke</title> 3, 14,
            that they should cast away their armsand withdraw themselves entirely from the military;
            however, it was said to them:
            <quote>Strike no one, be content with your pay</quote>.
            By commanding them that their own pay should suffice,
            he certainlydid not prohibit them from serving as soldiers</quote>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-d1e191">
          d. Likewise, <name ref="#Ambrose">Ambrose</name>, in book I of <title>De officiis</title>:
          <quote xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-Qd1e198">Fortitude, which protects the homeland from barbarians by war,
            or defends the weak at home,
            or allies from robbers,
            is fulljustice</quote>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-d1e206">
          e. Likewise, <name>Augustine</name>, <title>Vincentio Donatistae</title>:
          <quote xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-Qd1e210">If it were always blameworthy to cause persecution,
            it would not be written in the holy books:
            <quote>The one secretly slandering his neighbor, him I persecuted</quote></quote>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-d1e218">
          f. Likewise, <name ref="#Augustine">Augustine</name>, <title>Contra Petilianum</title>;
          <quote xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-Qd1e225">He who sins, does not sin by the authority of the Law,
            but against the authority of the Law.
            Therefore I ask you, whosevoice is it in the <title>Psalm</title>saying:
            <quote>The one secretly slandering his neighbor</quote>? etc.
            Seek therefore the cause and the measure of the persecution,
            and do not reprehend persecution in general.
            For we do not persecute you,
            except as truth persecutes falsehood</quote>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-d1e246">
          g. Likewise, <name>Augustine</name>, <title>Ad Bonifacium comitem</title>:
          <quote xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-Qd1e252">Whose voice do they think it is in the <title>Psalm</title>,
            where it is said:
            <quote>I will pursue my enemies, and I will catch them,
              and I will not turn back until they fail?</quote></quote>
        </p>
        <p xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-d1e260">
          From these things, therefore, it is concluded that the wicked are lawfully to be persecuted andattacked.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-d1e268">
          On the contrary: 1. Every war is waged either for repelling an injury from oneselfor from an ally,
          or for inflicting revenge.
          But the repelling of one's own injury is prohibited, <title>Matth.</title> 5, 39:
          <quote>If anyone strikes you on one cheek</quote> etc.;
          the repelling of the injury of allies is prohibited in Peter,
          when it was said to him:
          <quote>Put your sword back into its sheath</quote>, <title>Matth.</title> 26, 52;
          and the infliction of revenge is prohibited in <title>I Peter</title> 3, 9:
          <quote>Not returning evil for evil</quote> etc.
          Since, therefore, every cause of war is prohibited,
          it will be unlawful to wage war.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-d1e294">
          2. Likewise, <name>St. Gregory</name>:
          <quote xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-Qd1e298">Unless those carnal wars bore the figure of spiritual wars,
            never, as I think, would the books of Jewish histories have been handed down by the Apostles,
            to be read by the disciples of Christ, who came to teach peace</quote>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-d1e310">
          3. Likewise, the same <name>Gregory</name>:
          <quote>How would that description of wars benefit the disciples of Christ,
            to whom it is said by Jesus:
            <quote>My peace I give to you, my peaceI leave to you</quote>, <title>John</title> 14, 27;
            and:
            <quote>Not avenging yourselves</quote>, <title>Rom.</title> 12, 19,
            but
            <quote>rather take the injury and suffer the fraud</quote>, <title>I Cor.</title> 6, 7. </quote>
        </p>
        <p xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-d1e328">
          4. Likewise, the same<name>Gregory</name>:
          <quote>The <name>Apostle</name>, knowing that wars are no longer to be waged by us carnally,
            but rather the struggles of the soul against spiritual adversaries,
            gives the precept of military service to the soldiers of Christ, saying:
            <quote>Put on the armor of God,
              so that you may be able to stand against the snares of the devil</quote>, <title>Ephes.</title> 6, 11. </quote>
        </p>
        <p xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-d1e344">
          5. Likewise, <title>Matth.</title> 26, 52:
          <quote xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-Qd1e348" source="http://scta.info/resource/mt26_52">Everyone who takes up the sword will perish by the sword</quote>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-d1e354">
          From these things, therefore, it seems to be manifestly proven that in the time of grace it is entirely prohibited to wage war.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-d1e362">
          6. Likewise, that it is unlawful at all times to wage war and to persecute, is proven.
          For <name>St. Jerome</name>says, on that passage of <title>Gal.</title> 4, 29:
          <quote>He who was born according to the flesh persecuted him who was born according to the spirit</quote>:
          <quote xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-Qd1e375">He who is born according to the flesh, persecutes the spiritual man,
            but never does the spiritual man persecute the carnal</quote>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-d1e385">
          7. Likewise, of the members of the Church it is said, <title>Matth.</title> 5, 10:
          <quote>Blessed are those who suffer persecution for the sake of justice</quote>.
          Since, therefore, it belongs to the just to suffer persecution, not to cause it,
          it is concluded that to persecute the wicked will beunlawful.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-d1e398">
          8. Likewise, the precept of innocence is from the natural law, contained under that precept:
          <quote>What you hate to have done to you by another, see to it that you never do to another</quote>, <title>Tob.</title> 4, 16.
          Since therefore by persecution and war temporal and corporal harm is done,
          it will be against the precept of innocence to wage war or to persecute.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-d1e414">
          I respond: To wage war justly according to divine law is lawful,
          and is even commanded to the kings and princes of the earth,
          according to what <name>Augustine</name> says, <title>Ad Bonifacium comitem</title>,
          on that passage of the <title>Psalm</title>:
          <quote xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-Qd1e427"><quote>And now, kings, understand;
              be instructed, you who judge the earth. Serve the Lord in fear</quote>:
            How then do kings serve in fear,
            except by prohibiting and punishing with religious severity those things,
            which are against the Lord'scommands?
            For he serves in one way because he is a man,
            and in another way because he is a king.
            For because he is a man, he serves by livingfaithfully;
            because he is a king</quote>,
          he serves by fighting manfully according to the law of justice.
          But to wage war unjustly is unlawful and prohibited,
          according to what is shown in <title>Baruch</title> 3, 27,
          where it speaks of the giants, who were of great stature from the beginning, knowing war:
          <quote>The Lord did not choose these, nor did they find the way of discipline,
            therefore they perished</quote>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-d1e459">
          It should be noted, moreover, that in order to discern whether a war is just or unjust,
          one must consider the authority, the disposition, the intention,
          the condition, the merit, and the cause.
          The disposition and the authority must be considered in the person declaring the war;
          the condition and the intention in the person waging the war;
          the merit in the person enduring the war;
          and the cause in the person for whom the war is waged.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-d1e479">
          It must be said, therefore, that for a war to be just,
          it is required that the person declaring the war has a just disposition and a just authority.
          A just disposition, as <name ref="#Augustine">Augustine</name> says, <title>Ad Bonifacium comitem</title>:
          <quote xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-Qd1e495">Be peaceful in warring,
            so that you may lead those whom you conquer,
            to the utility of peace by defeatingthem.
            For blessed are <quote>the peacemakers, forthey shall be called children of God</quote></quote>.
          Likewise, the same <name ref="#Augustine">Augustine</name>,
          <quote xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-Qd1e511"><title>Contra Manichaeos</title>:
            The desire to harm, the cruelty of avenging,
            an implacable mind, the savagery of rebelling, the lust for dominating,
            these are the things, and whateveris similar,
            which are rightfully blamed in wars</quote>.
          — And a just authority, that is an ordered one,
          according to what <name ref="#Augustine">Augustine</name> shows.
          <quote xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-Qd1e526"><title>Contra Manichaeos</title>:
            When God or some legitimate power commands it,
            wars themselves are undertaken to be waged by good men,
            when they find themselves in that order of human affairs,
            where the order itself justly constrains them either to command such a thing,
            or to obey in such things</quote>.
          And later he adds:
          <quote xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-Qd1e539">That natural order of mortals accommodated to peace demands this,
            that the authority and counsel for undertaking a warbe in the hands of the princes</quote>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-d1e550">
          Likewise, in the personwaging the war, two things are required:
          a due intention and a due condition.
          A due intention, according to what <title>Augustine</title> says, <title>De verbis Domini</title>:
          <quote xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-Qd1e560">To serve in the military is not a crime,
            but to serve for the sake of plunder is a sin;
            nor is it criminal to manage public affairs,
            but to do so to increase riches is damnable</quote>.
          — Likewise, a due condition, that it not be a clerical person.
          Whence the Canon of <title>Pope John</title>, [<title>Causa</title>] XXIII, quaest. 8:
          <quote xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-Qd1e574">To exercise secular military service, to defend the land,
            to treat of battles and of arms, belongs to earthlypower</quote>.
          Likewise, in the same place, the <title>Canon</title> of the Council of Meaux says:
          <quote xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-Qd1e583">Whoever is seen to be of the clergyshould not take up military arms,
            because they cannot simultaneously serve God and the world</quote>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-d1e591">
          Likewise, in the person against whom the war is waged,
          a just merit must be considered,
          namely that he has justly deserved to be attacked or to suffer persecution.
          Whence <name ref="#Augustine">Augustine</name>, <title>Ad Bonifacium comitem</title>:
          <quote>There is an unjust persecution,
            which the impiousinflict upon the Church of Christ.
            For she is blessed, who suffers <quote>persecution</quote> <quote>for the sake of justice</quote>;
            but they are miserable, who suffer persecution on account of injustice.
            Therefore, she persecutes by loving, they by raging;
            she so as to correct, they so as to destroy</quote>.
          Likewise, the same <name ref="#Augustine">Augustine</name>, on the <title>Psalm</title>:
          <quote xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-Qd1e623">These two names, when we say <mentioned>man, sinner</mentioned>,
            are certainly not spoken in vain.
            Because he is a sinner, rebuke him; because he is a man, have mercy on him;
            nor will you entirely free the man, unless you have persecuted the sinner</quote>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-d1e637">
          Likewise, in the person of him for whom one fights,
          a just cause must be attended to,
          which is the uplifting of the good, the coercion of the wicked, the peace of all.
          Whence <name>Augustine</name>,
          <quote xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-Qd1e647"><title>De diversis Ecclesiae observationibus</title>:
            Among the trueworshippers of God even those warsare peaceful,
            which are waged not with cupidity or cruelty, but with a zeal for peace,
            so that the wicked may be coerced and the good uplifted</quote>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-d1e659">
          [To the objections]: 2. To that which is objected second,
          that <mentioned>carnal wars are handed down to be read by the disciples of Christ,
            only on account of the spiritual wars, which they signify</mentioned>,
          it must be said that he calls 'disciples of Christ' not Christians generally,
          but ecclesiastical men, to whom wars and arms are forbidden.
          Whence St. <name ref="#Ambrose">Ambrose</name>against the edict of the Emperor says:
          <quote>Against the Gothic soldiers my tears are my weapons:
            for such are the fortifications of a priest;
            otherwise I neither ought nor can resist</quote>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-d1e689">
          3. To the third which is objected, that it is said by Jesus <quote>my peace I give to you</quote>,
          it must be said that a just war is not repugnant to peace,
          rather it has peace as its end.
          Whence <name ref="#Augustine">Augustine</name>, <title>Ad Bonifacium</title>:
          <quote xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-Qd1e705">War ought to be of necessity,
            so that God may free from necessity and preserve in peace.
            For peace is not sought so that war may be exercised,
            but war is waged so that peace may be acquired</quote>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-d1e715">
          4. To the fourth, what <name>Gregory</name> says,
          that <mentioned>wars are no longer to be waged carnally</mentioned>,
          is to be understood as before, by ecclesiastical persons,
          for whom it was lawful to fight in the Old Testament,
          but it is not lawful in the New.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-d1e729">
          5. To the fifth which objects<quote>he who takes up the sword, will perish by the sword</quote>,
          <name>Augustine</name> responds, in book IIof <title>Contra Manichaeum</title>:
          <quote xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-Qd1e737">He takes up the sword who,
            with no superior and legitimate power commanding or granting it,
            is armed againstthe blood of another</quote>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-d1e747">
          6. To the sixth, what <name>Jerome</name> says,
          <mentioned>that the spiritual man never persecutes the carnal</mentioned>,
          <name ref="#Augustine">Augustine</name> and <name>Pope Pelagius</name> respond in [<title>Causa</title>] XXIII, quaest. 6:
          <quote xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-Qd1e758">Do not let the empty talk of men delay you,
            of those saying that the Church causes persecution,
            while she either represses those things which are committed,
            or seeks the salvation of souls.
            Such gossips err.
            He does not persecute except he who compels towards evil;
            but he who punishes an evil already done or prohibits it lest it be done,
            he does not persecute, but loves</quote>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-d1e781">
          7. To the seventh <name ref="#Augustine">Augustine</name> responds, <title>Ad Bonifacium comitem</title>:
          <quote>If the true Church is the one itself which suffers persecution, not the one which causes it,
            let it be asked of the <title>Apostle</title>,
            which Church did Sarah signify, when she was persecuting the handmaid</quote>,
          <title>Gen.</title> 21, 10.
          <quote>For the free mother, the heavenly Jerusalem, that is the true Church of God,
            he says is prefiguredin that woman</quote>, <title>Gal.</title> 4, 26,
          <quote>who afflicted the handmaid.
            If however we examine it better,
            the latter persecuted Sarah more by acting proudly than Sarah did by coercing;
            the latter did injury to the mistress,
            the former imposed discipline upon the proud one</quote>
        </p>
        <p xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-d1e813">
          8. To the eighth, which says <mentioned>that war is against the precept of innocence</mentioned>,
          it must be rejected.
          Whence <name ref="#Augustine">Augustine</name>, in the book <title>De civitate Dei</title>:
          <quote xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-Qd1e824" source="http://scta.info/resource/acdc-l2">It pertains to the duty of the innocent,
            not only to infer evil upon no one,
            but truly also to restrain from sins or to punish sin,
            so that the delinquent may be corrected by the experience,
            or others may be terrified by the example</quote>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="ahsh-l3p2in3t2s2q1t3d2m3c1-d1e834">
          1. But to the first, which objected that <mentioned>every cause of war is prohibited,
            because the inflicting of revenge and the repelling of injury is prohibited</mentioned>,
          the response is alreadyclear from the preceding.
          For the inflicting of revenge is not prohibited,
          except to a private person and out of the lust for revenge,
          but it is commanded to be inflicted by a judge out of the zeal for justice.
          Whence, <name>Augustine</name>, on <title>Joshua</title> 7, says:
          <quote>If we defer pursuing or avenging those things,
            by which God is vehemently offended,
            we provoke the patience of the divinity to anger.
            <quote>Did not Achan the son of Zerah, transgress the commandment of the Lord,
              and His anger rested upon all the people of Israel</quote>?
            And he wasone man,
            and would that he alone had perished in his wickedness</quote>.
          In a similar way, repelling an injury is a precept for him,
          who can usefully repel it from another.
          Whence <name>St. Ambrose</name>, in book I of <title>De officiis</title>:
          <quote>He who does not repel an injury from an ally, if he can,
            is as much in vice as he who inflicts it.
            Whence holy Moses, when he had seen a Hebrew receiving injury from an Egyptian</quote>,
          <title>Exod.</title> 2, 11-12,
          <quote>defended him, so that he struck down the Egyptian.
            Solomon also says: <quote>Rescue himwho is being led to death</quote></quote>.
          But that last point has some doubt, which will be determined below,
          in the Question concerning that precept of the Gospel:
          <quote>I say to you, do not resist the evildoer</quote>.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>